Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's daf דף daf is kuf
daled ק"ד, Kuf Daled, Bava Metzia בבא מציעא Bava Metzia 104. We
pick up at the Gemara גמרא Gemara at the very bottom, second
line from the bottom of kuf gimmel amud bais ק"ג עמוד ב,
Kuf Gimmel Amud Bais, 103b. We are also as for now recording
the 49th day of the Omer עומר, Omer, so good erev Shavuot
ערב שבועות. Erev Shavuot. And the Mishna משנה Mishna spoke about a
case where a person became a sharecropper or a tenant but renter
of a property and there was a well in it or a
tree in it,
and if the well or the tree dry up, he does not
get any reduction from his rental, you know, or from the he
doesn't get a greater portion
of
the crops, but if he specifically said, rent me this field with
the well, rent me this field with the tree, and then he
would get the free fruit of the tree, and then the well
or the tree dried up, then actually that would be a reduction
in his rent. So let's take a look at the Gemara גמרא,
Gemara, two lines from the bottom. Heychi dami היכי דמי, Heychi dami,
what's the case? Ileima diyavesh nahara אילימא דיבש נהרא, Ileima diyavesh nahara,
if when we say that the, you know, the irrigated field dried
up, not just a well, here we're talking about a case that
there was a
river, nahara rabba נהרא רבא, Nahara Rabba, amai ein menake lo michakuro
אמאי אין מנכה לו מחכורו. Amai ein menake lo michakuro. So here
we're talking about a case, excuse me, I said well before but
actually it'd be a river
with like canals that would feed it from the would feed the
field, irrigation canals. So if the reason that those irrigation canals dried
up is because the main river dried up, so the Gemara גמרא
Gemara says then even if that wasn't expressed and stipulated, that should
entitle him to a reduction in rent. Why? Neima makat medina hi
נימא מכת מדינה היא, Neima makat medina hi, let him say this
is something that's not just my bad luck, this is what the
tenant or the sharecropper says to the owner, it's something that the
entire community suffered, everybody in this town, you know, this is like
if there's a plague of locusts, everybody was affected by it, and
therefore I should not be paying normal prices that you would pay
for rental in a case where, you know, this is right now
the cost of rentals is a lot less. Now you might say
you were locked in, that was the amount you agreed to at
the beginning of the year, you know, there's always a risk that
there will be locusts or something, but the principle is when it's
just happens to this one person, that's his bad luck, if it
happens to everybody, then we have to adjust the rent appropriately. So
the Gemara גמרא Gemara says if that's the so that can't be
the case, because if that were the case, he would be able
to get a reduction in rent. Amar Rav Pappa diyavesh nahara zuta
אמר רב פפא דיבש נהרא זוטא. Amar Rav Pappa diyavesh nahara zuta.
Fine, so Rav Pappa רב פפא Rav Pappa says we're not talking
about the main river dried up, we're talking about the small river
dried up, the irrigation canal dried up, the actual irrigation canal dried
up. Okay, deamar lei דאמר ליה, Deamar lei, and he says to
him, ibai lach leasuyei bedavla איבעי לך לאתויי בדבלא. Ibai lach leasuyei
bedavla. Look, it's not my problem that the irrigation canal you thought
you were getting a field with an irrigation canal, okay, the irrigation
canal dried up, but you could still get the water from the
main river, so you don't get a reduction in rent. Now Tosafot
תוספות Tosafot asks the obvious question, he says, wait a minute, if
the only deciding factor is whether it's a makat medina מכת מדינה
Makat medina or not a makat medina מכת מדינה, Makat medina, and
then this is not the main river, it's just the irrigation canal,
you don't need the argument, hey, you can draw water from the,
you know, from the main river, just say, hey, it just happened
to you and you're not entitled to a reduction in rent. So
Tosafot תוספות Tosafot explains that gives reasons why the Gemara גמרא Gemara
might have said this, that maybe we're talking actually that it is
a makat medina מכת מדינה, Makat medina, everybody's irrigation canal dried up,
but nevertheless, you know, the water is still there from the main
river. And when do we say a makat medina מכת מדינה Makat
medina entitles you to reduction in rent? If it's if it's a
loss that there's no way to reverse. But here even though it
means more effort, you still are able to irrigate the field and
therefore even if it's a makat medina מכת מדינה, Makat medina, you
are not obligated in a reduction in rent. That's one of Tosafot's
תוספות Tosafot answers. Okay, top of kuf daled amud aleph ק"ד עמוד
א. Kuf Daled Amud Aleph. Amar Rav Pappa אמר רב פפא, Amar
Rav Pappa, says Rav Pappa רב פפא, Rav Pappa, hani tarti matnita
הני תרתי מתניתא, Hani tarti matnita, these two first Mishnayot משניות Mishnayot
that we talked, the Mishna משנה Mishna we talked both of them
yesterday, right, one was about the idea about it said about, you
know, that depending on what the practice is, is the practice to
to harvest with a sickle or is it to uproot the wheat,
is the practice to plow over after the wheat has been harvested,
that whatever the agreement is, you follow the normal agreement. Okay, that
and the other one we just taught about whether you're entitled to
reduction in rent, so those two he says mishkachan lehu bein bachachrunuta
bein bekablanuta משכחן להו בין בחכרונותא בין בקבלנותא. mishkachan lehu bein bachachrunuta
bein bekablanuta. They apply whether we're talking about a tenant farmer, like
you're paying rent, again, you would follow the minhag hamedina מנהג המדינה
Minhag hamedina and you would or wouldn't be entitled to a reduction
in rent when the, you know, tree dries up or or the
irrigation canal dries up, or whether it's sharecropping. Same basic point. Okay,
they're equally applicable to both. But mikan vailach מכאן ואילך, Mikan vailach,
the Mishnayot משניות Mishnayot we're going to see in the remainder. here
of this
פרק, perek, דאיתא בקבלנותא ליתא בחכירותא ודאיתא בחכירותא ליתא בקבלנותא. d'ita b'kabelnuta
leita b'chachiruta v'd'ita b'chachiruta leita b'kabelnuta. Some of them apply, if it's
applying to the case of sharecropping, it's not applying to a case
of rental, and it's applying to case of rental, it's not applying
to a case of sharecropping. They're talking only about one and not
the other, and as רש''י Rashi wisely says, we'll explain each one
when we get up to it. Okay, but be prepared as we
get to the next משנה. mishna. אם אמר לו חכור לי שדה
בית השלחין זה. Im amar lo chachor li sdei beit hashalechin zeh.
Okay, so if he says, however, if he says rent me this
field, this irrigated field, and he explicitly labels it an irrigated field,
then if the irrigation canals dry up, he's entitled to a reduction,
because it was clear that it was only because it was irrigated
that he was agreeing to that terms of that contract. So the
גמרא Gemara says ואמאי, v'amai, even if he calls it that, why
does that, why do we read that and interpret that as something
that entitles him to a reduction and say that that was a
factor in in the actual terms of the contract, in what he
agreed to pay for rent? Why don't we just say ואמאי לימא
ליה שמא בעלמא אמינא לך? v'amai leima leih shema b'alma amina lach?
Let the owner say, no, I'm just doing it like as as
an identifier. Which field am I renting you? I'm renting you the
irrigated field, the field, you know, that has these irrigation canals. It's
a way to describe it, but we're not it's not implicit that
that makes the the amount of the rental is a factor, you
know, is dependent on the fact that the irrigation canals were there.
Maybe it was just there as an identifier and not essential to
the terms of the contract. Okay, pretty interesting. But what's the source
of this? מי לא תניא? Mi lo tanya? Do we not teach
in a ברייתא? braita? המוכר לחבירו בית כור עפר אני מוכר לך.
Hamocher l'chaveiro beit kor afar ani mocher lach. If somebody says to
his friend, I'm going to sell you this field that is the
size of a בית כור, beit kor, which is something like 75,000
square אמות, amot, I think. So it's huge, okay? Let's say he
says this 10-acre field I'm selling you, אף על פי שאין בו
אלא לתך הגיעו. af al pi she'ein bo ela letech higio. Even
if it only winds up being five acres, half of that, you
can't get your money back. Now, that sounds absolutely crazy, right? You're
telling me the size of the field, and now it's different, and
I'm and I'm stuck with the field? So you know, so that
clearly is essential to the price I'm paying. So רב''ד Ravad says
that we're talking that he explicitly said this field, this field here,
you know, the one that goes from this boundary to that boundary
to that boundary, you're very clear exactly what the field is you're
describing, and you also call it a 10-acre field. So there, you
know, okay, that's what it's known as. People in town known it
as the 10-acre field. People they're off, it's eight acres, it's seven
acres, but it was very clear what the field what the boundaries
were. So then if it's very clear, again, none of that is
said here, but that's what the רב''ד Ravad says you have to
be talking about, then we don't say that you're entitled to a
reduction because that was just the way it's called. Okay, but then
the
גמרא Gemara says והוא דמיקרי בית כור, v'hu d'mikarei beit kor, but
that's only if that's really what the people in the town call
it. If the people in the town call it the 10-acre field,
you know, so we have a place a store here called the
Corner Cafe that's not on the corner. So if people call it,
you know, if that's the name, the 10-acre field, then you're just
describing it, you're just naming it, it's you're not actually what do
you call it, you're not actually promising that it's 10 acres. Pretty
amazing. כרם אני מוכר לך. Kerem ani mocher lach. If he says
I'm selling you a vineyard, and let's say it's very specifically clear
which plot of land he's talking about, so אף על פי שאין
בו גפנים הגיעו, af al pi she'ein bo gefanim higio, even if
it turns out that there are no vines in it, you know,
that's okay, you're stuck with it. Why? שלא מכר לו אלא שמו,
shelo machar lo ela shemo, because that's just what it was called,
like Martha's Vineyard. Are there any vineyards in Martha's Vineyard? I don't
know, I've never been there. Okay, but if you're selling I'm selling
you Martha's Vineyard, that's just the name of it. But the גמרא
Gemara says והוא דמיקרי כרמא, v'hu d'mikarei karma, provided that it genuinely
is called that. Again, this actually seems to be very unfair, but
we have to be assuming, yes, that is the name that it
is known by. And also as the רב''ד Ravad says, it's also
very clear what you're the plot of land you're referring to. So
the person could go, they could measure it, they could see if
there's vines, etc. פרדס Pardes similarly, פרדס אני מוכר לך אף על
פי שאין בו רימונים. pardes ani mocher lach af al pi she'ein
bo rimonim. If I'm selling you a פרדס, pardes, you know, an
orchard, then even if there are no
pomegranates—interestingly, it assumes that a standard פרדס pardes is a פרדס רימונים—הגיעו,
you're stuck, ושלא מכר לו אלא שמו, v'shelo machar lo ela shemo,
because that's what it's called, the place was called the orchard. Okay,
והוא דמיקרי פרדס, v'hu d'mikarei פרדס, as long as that's what it's
called. אלמא אמר ליה שמא בעלמא אמרי לך. Alma amar leih shema
b'alma amri lach. So you see that people can basically say I
am, you know, like רחל בתך הקטנה. Rachel bitcha haktana. רש''י Rashi
says oh, you'll get another girl and you'll call her רחל, Rachel,
No, בתך. bitcha. You know, so anyway, so people but there are
times where people could just say that's just the way to describe
it. Now, this case is much better because in this case, it
actually did have a tree and it actually did have an irrigation
canal, so maybe you were just describing it and you were. identifying
it, and it was not saying that it was essential to the
terms of the contract and that if the tree dried up or
the irrigation canal dried up that you would be entitled to a
deduction in rent. Okay, that makes sense. Maybe how do you know
that it's essential to the terms of the contract? So אמר סו
ama so הכא נמי נימא לשמא בעלמא אמר לך hakha nami neima
lishama be'alma amar lakh אמר שמואל amar Shmuel see שמואל לא קשיא
Shmuel lo kashya הא דאמר ליה מחכיר לחוקר ha de'amar lei makhir
lekhoker הא דאמר ליה חוקר למחכיר ha de'amar lei khoker lemakhir it
depends who's saying it. If the seller or the owner is saying
to the person to the person leasing it is saying
this field with the irrigation canal, so he's not saying if the
seller is the one making the stipulation, so we don't assume that
he's saying it in order to make life harder for him and
to say that if it dries up you're going to get a
deduction. He's just going to be saying it as a description. However,
if the borrower if the one leasing it says I am leasing
this field with this field with the irrigation canal, then we assume
that it is essential to the terms of the contract. Okay, so
it's a little funny because in the end you write up a
contract that both parties sign exactly or that, you know, what does
it mean who said it? In the end are we talking about
a verbal contract? There are witnesses, not a written contract. All right,
but anyway, that's the distinction. אמר ליה מחכיר לחוקר amar lei makhir
lekhoker שמא בעלמא shma be'alma if it's the owner who is who
is who is saying the field the field with the irrigation canal,
then he's just describing it.
אמר ליה חוקר למחכיר amar lei khoker lemakhir if the one renting
it is saying it קפידא k'fida then he's saying no, I am
renting it because it has this and that's why I am agreeing
to the price. רבינא אמר Ravina amar Ravina said אידי ואידי דאמר
ליה מחכיר לחוקר idi ve'idi de'amar lei makhir lekhoker we're talking about
both that the owner says it. תוספות Tosafot actually says or both
that the renter says it. It doesn't really matter who's saying it,
okay? מדקאמר זה mideka'amar zeh מכלל דקאי בגווה עסקינן mikhlal dekai begava
askinan if you're saying I am renting this, it sounds again like
this is an oral contract, it's not a written contract. So therefore
we could be talking about who's the person saying it. But if
you're saying I am renting you or I am renting from you
this field with the irrigation canal, so the fact that you're saying
this means you're in the field itself. So if you're in the
field itself, just say this field. Why do you have to say
this field with the irrigation canal? You don't need to describe it,
you're right there, you said this. This already described it. So בית
השלחין למה לי למימר beit hashlakhin lama li lemeimar why do you
have to say with the irrigation? So כדקאמר ליה למה לי למימר
kedeka'amar lei lama li lemeimar דאמר ליה בית השלחין כדקאי השתא de'amar
lei beit hashlakhin kedekai hashta because what you're saying is that I
am renting it assuming it's going to remain an irrigated field like
it is right now with these irrigation canals. So once you said
this and it was clear what you were talking about, you did
not need to also name it an irrigation field or a field
with a tree. And since you did, that was clear then whoever
was the one who did the naming that it was understood that
that was part of the terms of the contract. Okay, that makes
a lot of sense. Let's take a look now at the next
משנה. mishna. המקבל שדה מחברו והובירה. hamikabel sadeh mechavero vehovirah. This is
going to be a case that it's noticed that it's קבלנות, kablanut,
מקבל, mikabel, only by sharecropping. Somebody was a sharecropper and the owner's
going to get paid with a portion of the produce, a quarter,
a third, whatever it is. And the guy who took it under
who agreed to be the sharecropper decided not to work it. He
got lazy. He wasn't worth his effort. Now, this wouldn't so what's
the consequence? Now, this would not be a question if it was
a rental. If it was a rental, then the owner isn't getting
a portion of the produce. The owner is getting whatever the flat
fee is. He doesn't care what you wind up doing with it,
work, you know, if you plow it or you don't plow it,
he's getting his flat fee regardless. But if what he was getting
was a portion of the produce and the case of קבלנות kablanut
and you did not work it, what's the consequence? He let it
lay fallow. שמינו אותה כמה ראויה
לעשות. shaminu otah kamah ra'uyah la'asot. You estimate how much would a
field like this produce, what would be the average we could assume,
I mean the net obviously minus all the expenses. ונותן לו venoten
lo and then the and then the sharecropper is obligated to give
him a third of what the net profits would have been or
whatever, or maybe if he got a third of the gross, whatever
the agreement was, you estimate what it would have turned out to
be and he has to pay the owner even if he did
not work the field. שכך כותב לו shekakh kotev lo because that's
what's written in the שטר. shtar. אם אוביר ולא אעביד im ovir
velo a'avid if I let it lay fallow and I don't work
it אשלם במיטבא ashalem bemetava I will pay with the best of
produce. Now, if it literally is written in the שטר, shtar, then
what's the חידוש chidush of the משנה? mishna? So let's take a
look at the first line of the גמרא, Gemara, there's a lot
of interesting debate in the ראשונים Rishonim what this next גמרא Gemara
is going to mean. רבי מאיר היה דורש לשון הדיוט. Rabbi Meir
hayah doresh leshon hedyot. So now the גמרא Gemara says Rabbi Meir
would would extrapolate, דורש, doresh, like you're דורש א פסוק, doresh a
pasuk, the common language in the in documents, okay, the language of
the vernacular that the people would use that was not authorized by
חז"ל Chazal but it was a standard language which was used. רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* would interpret it or explicate it. דתניא detanya, *Detanya*,
we taught in the ברייתא Baraisa, *Baraita*, רבי מאיר אומר *Rabbi Meir
omer*, אם im אוביר ולא עביד אשלם במיטבא *im oveir velo avid
ashalem bemetiva*. So now we see that ברייתא braisa, *Baraita* is making
clear that our משנה Mishnah *Mishna* is רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says this is the language that if you let
it lay fallow you have to pay and therefore that is the
הלכה *Halacha*. Now what does this mean דורש לשון הדיוט doresh lashon
hedyot? *doresh leshon hedyot*? If it's in the שטר Shtar *shtar*, you
don't need to be דורש *doresh*. That's the agreement. So there is
two or three explanations in the ראשונים *Rishonim*. If you take a
look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says שהרגילו הדיוטות לכתוב
שלא כתקנת חכמים היה דורש הלשון לפסוק הדין אחריו *shehirgilu hedyotot lichtov
shelo ketakanat chachamim haya doresh halashon lifsok hadin
acharav*. Even though it was not according to what the חכמים *chachamim*
established, he would give it actual weight. Now of course he would
give it weight. It's in the document. But the one way this
is explained is that even if it would not be legally binding
from a technical perspective. Why would this not legally be binding? Maybe
it's a case of אסמכתא asmachta, *asmachta*. We'll see about
אסמכתא *asmachta later*. Maybe because you're promising something and exaggerating and you're
not serious about that obligation. You might have said how do we
know you really can obligate yourself with such a thing? Maybe you
never really expected that you would have to pay. Maybe it's אסמכתא
*asmachta*. So maybe that's the point. And nevertheless since it's in the
שטר shtar *shtar* and it's a standard usage, we're going to treat
it as binding. Or maybe it's not sometimes there's all these laws
about how you have to stipulate conditions. We're going to see later
a whole case about קידושין kiddushin, *Kiddushin* with all these which
would undermine a קידושין kiddushin *Kiddushin* because of a language and they
wouldn't worry that it would have to satisfy all of the normal
requirements of a תנאי tnai. *tenai*. So that's one way of understanding
it. He would give it הלכה *halakhic* weight even though there might
be from a technical הלכה *Halacha* perspective there could be some technical
problems that it might not actually work. תוספות Tosfos, *Tosafot* has a
different explanation. If you look at תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*, היה דורש לשון
הדיוט doresh lashon hedyot. *haya doresh leshon hedyot*, לשונות שלא תקנו חכמים
לכתוב *leshonot shelo tiknu chachamim lichtov*. There's no problem with it, it
just was not established by the rabbis to write it. אלא הדיוטות
הורגלו לכותבם היה דורש ואפילו לא כתב כאילו נכתב *ela hedyotot horgilu
lechotvam haya doresh veafilu lo katav keilu nichtav*. And the חידוש *chiddush*
is דורש *doresh* means it's a funny word of דורש *doresh*, but
דורש *doresh* maybe have the same way חז"ל *Chazal* can read something
into the פסוק *pasuk* that's not exactly there. So if this was
a standard language in a document, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* would read
it into the document even if it hadn't been written. Like the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sometimes has a discussion of אחריות achrayus טעות סופר
*achrayut ta'ut sofer*. Do we assume it belongs there and therefore even
if it's not there it's as if it is there? So that
is it doesn't exactly fit the language of דורש *doresh*, but that
is what is being said. דאי דוקא כשכתב מאי היה דורש פשיטא
דשדינן כמו שכתב דלאו אסמכתא הוא *de'i davka keshakatav mai haya doresh
peshita deshadinan kemo shekatav delav asmachta hu*. So תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* says
don't tell me it's an אסמכתא *asmachta*. It's not an אסמכתא *asmachta*.
You're not promising to give a million dollars, you're just promising to
give the owner what he normally would have earned. That's a reasonable
obligation. So if it's written in the שטר shtar, *shtar* and it's
not an אסמכתא *asmachta*, what's this idea of דורש לשון הדיוט doresh
lashon hedyot, *doresh leshon hedyot*? That's just something you obligated yourself for.
So for תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*, דורש לשון הדיוט lashon hedyot. *doresh leshon
hedyot* means since it was standard in the document, he would פסק
*pasken* like it even if it wasn't written. So those are two
basic explanations. It has the weight of an obligation because it is
standard even if there are technical problems with it, or it's like
it's written because it was usually written and standard to be written.
We always see it there even if wasn't written explicitly. There's a
third possibility which is like דורש *doresh* really means. Even though the
language could be understood differently you would approach it like a פסוק
*pasuk* to learn out specific הלכות *halachot* and to apply it very
rigorously. Although here that's not exactly clear how that fits this case
because this case seems very straightforward. You don't need much of a
דרשה *derasha*. Now we're going to see a list of other people
that would be of other תנאים tna'im *Tannaim* that would be דורש
לשון הדיוט lashon hedyot. *doresh leshon hedyot*. Let's take a look. רבי
יהודה היה דורש לשון הדיוט lashon hedyot *Rabbi Yehuda haya doresh leshon
hedyot*. דתניא detanya, *Detanya*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* would do this also.
אומר אדם מביא קרבן עשיר על אשתו *omer adam mevi korban ashir
al ishto*. A person, sometimes when there's an obligation for a קרבן
*korban*, it could it would depend whether the person is poor or
rich whether they give a big קרבן *korban* like a sheep or
a small one like a bird. And if a woman would be
obligated in that קרבן *korban*, only some קרבנות korbanos *korbanot* operate like
that, let's say she gave birth or she has צרעת *tzara'at*, then
even though she technically might not have any money in her own
name, since the husband has money, he would be the one that
would pay for the קרבן *korban* and it would go based on
his wealth and if he was rich he would pay at the
top of that scale. וכן כל קרבן וקרבן שהיא חייבת *vechen kol
korban vekorban shehi chayavet*. And not only that, he the husband would
actually have to pay every קרבן *korban* she'd be obligated in. תוספות
*Tosafot* says, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* תוספות *Tosafot* says that it's not that
she just made a vow to obligate herself in a קרבן *korban*,
some type of a קרבן *korban* that she's obligated in
because she sinned and she has to bring a קרבן *korban* or
because she gave birth, other types of. reasons that are obligations that
are imposed upon her.
Now why does he have to be the one to provide for
the קרבן? שכך כותב לה shekach kosev la because this is what
he would write, אחריות דאית לי על מן קדמת דנא. achrayus de'isli
ala min kadmas dena. So if a husband writes in the כתובה,
kesubah, I accept upon myself obligations that you had prior to this.
Okay, now, now okay, but like there's a line missing here. I
mean there's a debate of רשי Rashi and תוספות, but the way
תוספות says it, what this is really saying is not only is
he obligated to pay for the קרבנות korbanos, that obligations she incurs
during the marriage, but even if she entered into the marriage obligated
in קרבנות, he is obligated, again, that were externally imposed, he is
obligated to provide it because that is the language in the כתובה.
kesubah. Now again, if it's the language in the כתובה, kesubah, then
what's דורש לשון הדיוט? lashon hedyot So תוספות would say that means
even if it's not in the כתובה, kesubah, it's like it's in
the כתובה. kesubah. You know, the other explanation might say maybe it
was flowery, maybe he didn't mean it seriously, and nevertheless, maybe it's
אסמכתא, but nevertheless we treat it seriously. Okay. הלל הזקן היה דורש
לשון הדיוט,
Hillel Hazaken hayah doresh
lashon hedyot,
Hillel the Elder, the one who established פרוזבול, prosbul, would also be
prepared to be דורש לשון הדיוט. דתניא, detanya and this is the
most radical application about it, אנשי אלכסנדריה היו מקדשין נשיהן. Anshei Alexandriah
hayu mekaddshin nesheihem.
People of Alexandria would do קידושין, kiddushin? ובשעת כניסתן לחופה, u'vishas knisasam
lachuppah,
and when it was time for the actual חופה, chuppah, which might
have been years later, they were finally ready to actually have the
חופה chuppah and then not only give the ring but stand under
the חופה, chuppah, say שבע ברכות sheva berachos and start living together
as husband and wife because from the קידושין kiddushin they were still
living apart.
And in that moment באים אחרים וחוטפין אותם מהם. ba'im acherim ve'chotfin
osam meihem. So at that moment, you know, people would come and
steal the wives away before now what does it exactly mean? Does
it mean they would take them out from under the חופה chuppah
and rape them? Does it mean they would be seduced by other
men and wind up leaving and wind up, you know, going and
living with a guy who's not the guy who did קידושין? kiddushin.
So whether it was rape, whether it was seduction, it sounds a
little more like rape. But the point was that these women were
taken by other men after קידושין kiddushin, before the חופה. chuppah. And
reasonably it says בקשו חכמים לעשות בניהם ממזרים. bikshu chachamim la'asos b'neihem
mamzeirim.
Reasonably then you would say the kids are ממזרים mamzeirim because the
kids were born from the union with these other men that were
not the man that did the קידושין. kiddushin אמר להם הלל הזקן,
amar lahem Hillel Hazaken, Hillel the Elder said, הביאו לי כתובת אמכם.
heviu li kesubas imchem. Go bring me your mother's כתובה. kesubah. Okay.
הביאו לו כתובת אמן, heviu lo kesubas iman, they brought them their
mother's כתובה, kesubah, ומצא שכתוב בהן, u'matza she-kasuv bahen, לכשתכנסי לחופה הרי
לי לאינתו, lekhshe-tikhnasi lachuppah harei li le'intu, when I bring you under
the חופה chuppah you will be my wife.
So even though they did the קידושין, kiddushin the language in the
כתובה kesubah said that when, you know, he gave her the קידושין
kiddushin, and said to her, when I bring you under the חופה
chuppah you will be my wife. So Hillel decided to read that
not like you'll be my wife because then we'll start living together,
but he read it as a very technical תנאי. tnai, ולא עשו
בניהם ממזרים, ve-lo asu b'neihem mamzeirim, their kids were not ממזרים mamzeirim
because he said it was a תנאי, tnai, it was a condition.
It meant that only if I succeed in bringing you under the
חופה chuppah and we have the חופה, chuppah, then retroactively the קידושין
kiddushin, I gave you will be קידושין, but if we never get
to the point of the חופה, chuppah, we never will have had
קידושין, retroactively it never would have taken effect. So here's a case
where it seems very much not like תוספות is saying, that it
was written in it, but also that the language could easily have
meant something much more flowery, or even if it was intended as
a תנאי, does it really is it really formulated properly like the
laws of תנאים require? And nevertheless he gave it halakhic weight. And
this obviously was the most consequential. רבי יהושע בן קרחה אמר, Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha amar, okay sorry, I skipped a line. רבי יהושע
בן קרחה היה דורש לשון הדיוט. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha hayah doresh
lashon hedyot. Similarly רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha would
explain לשון הדיוט. דתניא, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita רבי יהושע
בן קרחה אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha omer, המלווה חברו לא ימשכננו
יותר מחובו. hamalveh chavero lo yamshichennu yoser michovo.
If somebody lends somebody money, you're not allowed to take collateral more
than the value of the loan.
Often the person has a piece of collateral that isn't exactly the
value of the loan. So you lend me $100, I don't have
anything to my name except my iPhone. You want collateral, my iPhone's
worth $1000. Okay, I have no choice, I give you my iPhone.
Okay and you know and if in the end I can't pay
you the $100, maybe you'll keep the iPhone and give me back
$900, I don't know, we'll figure it out. But he says no,
you're not allowed to take collateral more than the loan. Why? שכך
כותב לו she-kach kosev lo
because this is what I would write to the creditor. If he
took my iPhone, but I say, hey, you know, I need my
iPhone back for a while, I do my business on it. Like,
give it back to me for a week and then I'll give
it back to you. So then we would write a document that
said that the collateral had been returned. And here's what we would
write in the document. So we would write תשלומתא דאית לך עלי
Tashlumsa de'is lach alay
the payment that you have against me, the money I owe you,
you know, so כל קביל דיכי kol k'veil dikhi is you know
this collateral is is equal to the cost to the amount of
this collateral. So in the document that would show that you know
I had taken the collateral back but you could take it back
from me if I didn't pay and so on, that document would
say that the money I owe you, that is the value of
this collateral. So that's that, so therefore if that's what the document
is going to say and if we're going to treat it that
way seriously because we're going to be דורש לשון הדיוט, so that
means that you can't you know don't take my iPhone because if
the document we're going to use is going to say the money
I owe you that's what this collateral is worth, then you're going
to be able to take my thousand dollar iPhone for a hundred
dollar debt. So since that's what we say in the document, that's
what then we have to be careful that you don't take collateral
more than the debt. But now the גמרא Gemara asks a reason-some-more
question. What's the purpose of the document? So the גמרא Gemara says
טעמא דכתב להכי ta'ama dechasav lehachi so okay
because he wrote that document that what does that do? That presumably
lets the guy I don't know take the collateral back or you
know
so what would be the consequence if he didn't write the document?
אי לאו כתב להכי iy lav kasav lehachi and he didn't write
it that way לא קניא? lo kanya? Would we say that the
original owner would not still I mean excuse me the creditor would
not still have rights to the collateral? And the only reason presumably
we're writing a document that I the borrower give you the creditor
when I get my collateral back is presumably so that you still
have rights to the collateral. Why else would we need that document?
But the גמרא Gemara is saying but we don't need a document
to say that the creditor still has rights to the collateral. ואמר
רבי יוחנן, ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says משכנו והשיב
לו המשכון ומת שם גובה מן הבנים mashkeno veheshiv lo hamashkon umas
sham goveh min habanim
that if you know
ראובן Reuven borrowed money from שמעון, Shimon, you know ראובן Reuven gave
and שמעון Shimon took ראובן's Reuven's iPhone and then שמעון Shimon gave
the iPhone back to ראובן Reuven and ראובן Reuven died, so normally
you know what we would say is a creditor does not have
rights to seize the loan from chattel מטלטלין metaltelin of the orphans,
only from landed estate that is left over to the orphans. He
only has a lien on landed estate. But because this was originally
collateral in the hands of the creditor, even when it was temporarily
returned to the borrower, the creditor still has ownership and rights to
it and he can take it from the orphans of the borrower.
So you don't need the document to ensure that the creditor still
has rights to it. So what is the point of writing this
whole document anyway? So top of כד עמוד ב, kaf daled amud
beis, so the גמרא Gemara. says הני כתיבי לגרעון. hanei k'sive legira'on.
No, it works for depreciation. Now what does depreciation mean? So רש"י
says depreciation means that if the collateral because of my using of
it becomes worth less, then the creditor is entitled not just to
get the collateral back but also to get the difference between the
collateral and the loan. He's entitled to get the full amount back.
Of course that doesn't anyway you would assume that's
true and besides which that doesn't really fit the language when I
insist that the value of the loan is you know equal to
the collateral.
So the ספרדי ראשונים Sefardi Rishonim say the opposite. The ספרדי ראשונים
Sefardi Rishonim say by emphasizing that the value of the loan is
equal to the collateral, what that means is is that if the
collateral depreciates, you the creditor still can only take the collateral because
we have identified said that that collateral is equal to the value
of the loan. That works better in terms of the language. Okay,
but that's also why you should not take collateral more because then
you'll because then you'll be entitled to getting much more than you
deserve. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi top of כד עמוד ב. kaf daled
amud beis. רבי יוסי היה דורש לשון הדיוט. Rabbi Yossi haya doresh
lashon hedyot. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would similarly explain לשון הדיוט. דתניא
it taught in a ברייתא, רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yossi omer מקום
שנהגו לעשות כתובה כמלווה גובה כמלווה. makom she'nahagu la'asos k'suva kemilve goveh
kemilve. When they would make a כתובה k'suva like a normal loan,
they would use normal loan language and say like you know I
accept on myself אחריות or whatever, then it would function like a
normal loan. What does this mean? רש"י says we're talking about the
general assumption is we're talking well it's actually clear from the גמרא.
Gemara We're talking about when the you know the bride brings in
a dowry into the כתובה. k'suva. Nowadays it's like like you know
think about Fiddler on the Roof, you know two geese, four down
pillows, whatever she would bring in. That would be written up in
the כתובה k'suva and the amount would be written. You know she
brought X, Y, and Z into into it and it was worth
two hundred dollars, five hundred dollars, whatever it would be. What would
be the point of that? The point of that would be she
brings it into the estate, the husband has ownership of it now.
This is what's called נכסי צאן ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel. And if
he dies before she. she dies or they get divorced, she's entitled
to take $500 back out of the estate because that was the
value of what she brought in to the marriage that the husband
took ownership over. That's the that's what we're talking about right now.
If it is done like a normal debt, meaning as we'll see,
this probably just means in contrast to what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say in a minute, where it is disproportionate to the
amount brought in. But if it is exactly proportionate to the amount
brought in, so literally she brought in $500 worth of, you know,
geese and down pillows or whatever, then, okay, then you collect the
husband, you know, when it's time for the wife to get divorced
or if the wife gets divorced or the husband dies, she collects
the full amount that was brought in. And if it says it
in the כתובה Ketubah and she hasn't brought it in, then the
husband has a right to demand from her or her father that
that is gets contributed to the marital estate, okay, to, you know,
to their marital household. However, it'll be clearer now when it's contrasted.
לכפול, Likhfol, if the practice however is to write double the amount
that actually was brought in, גובה מחצה, gova mechtza, then you only
collect half. And that works both ways, meaning, let's say the amount
that the woman would bring in with the pillows and the geese
or whatever was really worth was worth $500, like we said, but
the practice in the place to make it sound like, oh, she
brought so much into the marriage, they would always double the amount.
It was worth $1,000. So if that's the practice in that place,
then the husband, if she hasn't brought it into the marriage, he
can't go to the father and demand $1,000 worth of stuff since
you always write double, he can only demand 500, half of the
amount written in. Similarly, if they get divorced or the husband dies,
the wife can't take 1,000 out of the estate, she can only
take 500, it's understood that this is double the actual amount. And
maybe that's what the לשון הדיוט here is, again, this is not
like it's not written, it's of course it's written, the לשון הדיוט
is that even though a formal approach to a שטר would say
it says $1,000, you owe $1,000, but if it's understood that it
was a doubled amount, we would treat it as a doubled amount
and only go by the actual amount. I should mention, and here's
a good point to mention that in our practice, that is when
we write in the כתובה, Ketubah, you know, that that the bride
brought in, במאני דלבושא, bimani delivusha, בשימושי דירה, beshimushei direh, בשימושי דערסא,
beshimushei dearsa, בין במדא בין בתכשיטין, bein bamadah bein betachshitin, all the
stuff she brought in, gold, silver, jewelry, you know, bedding, etc., so
that's represents what we're talking about, the dowry she's bringing in. And
it says הכל קיבל עליו החתן במאה זקוקים כסף צרוף. hakol kibel
alav hachatan bemeah zkukim kesef tzaruf.
The חתן chasan accepted it upon himself as a value, he agreed
to assign the value as 100 זקוק zkuk of כסף. kesef. Now,
and then we have another 100 זקוק zkuk for a תוספת tosefet
and we get 200 זקוק. zkuk. That זקוק zkuk is not a
זוז. zuz. That זקוק zkuk is worth like 50 times a זוז.
zuz. What the problem was was in the time of medieval אשכנז,
Ashkenaz, silver was worth very little and 200 זוז zuz was a
very, very small amount and the woman was not protected. So what
they did to protect the woman was that they said we are
going to assign the value of the dowry, even if you just
bring in one dollar, we're going to assign the value of the
dowry and claim that it is 100 זקוק zkuk of silver, which
is a much larger amount, like $10,000,
okay, and then plus another 100 זקוק zkuk for the תוספת, tosefet,
so you're going to be you're going to be protected with not
200 זוז, zuz, but 200 זקוק. zkuk. So anyway, that's very similar
here, but there it was intended to be a real obligation, not
as an exaggerated double amount as a way to protect the woman.
Okay, so נהרבלאי גבו תילשא, Naharbalai gavu tilsha, in this place of
נהרבלאי, Naharbalai, they really only collected a third of the amount written
because presumably they would write three times the amount that was actually
brought in.
מרימר מגבי משבחא, Maremar magbi misifcha, מרימר Maremar however was said nope,
when it comes time to collect, whether it's the groom collecting from
the father or whether it's the bride, you know, collecting from the
estate if they get divorced or he dies, he would treat it
completely literal and even the extra amount that was added, the double,
the increased amount, he would treat it all literally, going against the
thread here, which the גמרא Gemara says. אמר ליה רבינא למרימר, Amrei
leih Ravina leMaremar, so רבינא Ravina said back to מרימר, Maremar, והתניא
לכפול גובה מחצה, vehatanya likhfol gova mechtza, but the ברייתא says if
the practice is to double, you only collect half. So, and here
the practice is to write an excessive amount, so why are you
prepared to collect it all? So לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not
difficult. הא דקני מיניה הא דלא קני מיניה, ha dekani minei ha
delo kani minei, it matters whether you did a קניין סודר kinyan
sudar like a handkerchief, you know, between the groom and the חתן
chasan and the bride's father who normally would be the one contributing
to the dowry. The קניין kinyan would be to affirm that you
really mean the full amount that's written in the כתובה Ketubah and
you don't mean it as an exaggeration. All right, and that's by
the way in our days we do a קניין kinyan on the
כתובה Ketubah and it is the full amount.
רבינא משבח וכתב לברתיה, Ravina mishpach vekasiv levarteh, רבינא Ravina would do
this משבח, mishpach, like שבח, shevach, like he would be excessive and
write for his daughter like double the amount that was actually being
contributed, as was the practice. אמרו ליה נקני מיניה דמר. Amru lei
nikni minei demar. So when it came time to write up the
כתובה, Kesuvah, they said, let's do a קנין Kinyan on your obligation.
אמר להו Amar lehu and he said, אי מקני לא מכפל אי
מכפל לא מקני. ei makni la michpal ei michpal la makni. I'll
do... if you want me to do a קנין, Kinyan, I'm not
going to write double the amount. If I'm going to write double
the amount, I'm not going to do a קנין, Kinyan, which is
exactly the point we said before that when it's not... it's done
without a קנין, Kinyan, so then it's an actual record of what
was brought in. Right? Let me actually explain it more than I
did before. If it's not a קנין, Kinyan, then it's just a
reality. The bride brought in this property and we're just recording it.
And if the reality is that it was... we're recording a number
that's double and it's understood it's double, then the reality of what
she actually brought in was half of the amount that was brought
in, and therefore that's what she's entitled to. So without a קנין,
Kinyan, she's entitled to half because that's the objective reality of what
she brought in. But you can obligate yourself to anything you want
through a קנין. Kinyan. I could owe you no money and we
could do a קנין Kinyan and I could assume a million dollar
debt to you and that would be binding. So even if she
didn't bring it in, if a קנין Kinyan was done, then that
creates the real debt. That creates the real obligation for the bride
or the father to contribute that amount to the marriage, and that
allows the woman to take it out. Okay, so if the practice
is to write double the amount and there's no קנין Kinyan done,
then you ask yourself, what was the actual amount brought into the
marriage? It was half the amount written, that's what we know based
on the practice, and that's what she's entitled to take out. If
there was a קנין, Kinyan, then we don't care what the amount
was that she actually brought in. The קנין Kinyan obligates you to
what is written. And that's how our כתובה Kesuvah works right now.
Okay, ההוא גברא דאמר להו. hahu gavra de'amar lehu.
A man said when he was dying, הבו לה ארבע מאה זוזי
לברתי בכתובתה. havu la arba me'ah zuzei lebartei biksuvasa. I'm about to
die and I want to make sure that you give 400 זוז
zuz from my estate for my daughter for her כתובה. Kesuvah. So
now we want to know, what does he mean? Right? And now
he died. שלח רב אחא בריה דרב אויא לקמיה דרב אשי. shalach
Rav Acha berei deRav Avya lekamei deRav Ashi. So the question was
sent to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, ארבע מאה דאינון תמני מאה? arba
me'ah de'inun tamni me'ah?
Does he mean 400 זוז zuz is the actual amount he wants
to contribute to the כתובה Kesuvah and then it would be written
in the כתובה Kesuvah 800? או ארבע מאה זוזי דאינון מאתן? o
arba me'ah zuzei de'inun masan?
Or does he mean write 400 in the כתובה Kesuvah and he's
really only contributing 200? What does he mean when he says 400?
Really give her 400 זוז zuz or write 400 זוז zuz in
her כתובה? Kesuvah? So אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, רב אשי
Rav Ashi says, let's look at the language he said. חזינן, chazinan,
let's take a look. אי אמר הבו לה ארבע מאה זוזי, ei
amar havu la arba me'ah zuzei, give her 400, or excuse me,
הבו לה, havu la, give her, then ארבע מאה דאינון תמני מאה.
arba me'ah de'inun tamni me'ah. Then it means 400 that's 800. Meaning,
give her 400 is I want her to actually get 400 זוז.
zuz. Okay,
then you'll write in the כתובה Kesuvah 800, but I want you
to give her 400. So give her, you give her the 400.
אי אמר כתבו לה, ei amar kivsu la, if he says write
for her 400 in her כתובה, Kesuvah, then ארבע מאה זוזי דאינון
מאתן, arba me'ah zuzei de'inun masan, then write 400 and actually give
her 200. Very, very logical. Did he say give her the money
or this is what you should write in her כתובה? Kesuvah? אמר
רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, איכא דאמרי ika de'amri some say, אמר
רב אשי חזינן. amar Rav Ashi chazinan.
No, no, no, we look at something else. אי אמר לכתובתה, ei
amar liksuvasa,
if he says give her 400 for her כתובה, Kesuvah, ארבע מאה
דאינון תמני מאה, arba me'ah de'inun tamni me'ah, then it means really
give her 400, you'll write 800, really give 400, because I mean
for the sake of her כתובה, Kesuvah, for her dowry, and I'm
talking about what you're actually going to give her is 400. אי
אמר בכתובתה, ei amar biksuvasa,
put 400 in her כתובה, Kesuvah, then I mean what you're writing
in the document. Then ארבע מאה זוזי דאינון מאתן, arba me'ah zuzei
de'inun masan, I mean write 400 in the כתובה Kesuvah which really
means she's only going to get 200. That also makes a lot
of sense. For her כתובה Kesuvah means different than putting it in
her כתובה. Kesuvah. But the גמרא Gemara says, ולא היא. velo hi.
The גמרא Gemara rejects this last distinction because not everybody is such
a legal scholar and they would distinguish between ב be and ל.
le. לא שנא דאמר לכתובתה לא שנא דאמר בכתובתה ארבע מאה זוזי
דאינון מאתן. lo shenan de'amar liksuvasa lo shenan de'amar biksuvasa arba me'ah
zuzei de'inun masan.
Whenever he says in the כתובה, Kesuvah, for the כתובה, Kesuvah, if
you mention the כתובה, Kesuvah, then you mean that's the amount written
in the כתובה. Kesuvah. So 400 is written and he's actually just
contributing 200. עד דאמר הבו לה סתמא. ad de'amar havu la stama.
If he just says give her and he doesn't say like write
in the כתובה Kesuvah or whatever or mention the like say the
word כתובה, Kesuvah, give her means I really want her to get
that. Give her for her marriage or whatever. This is sounding like
even if he says give her, if he says give her with
the word כתובה, Kesuvah, that we would actually interpret it to mean
the lesser amount and not the full amount. It's not exactly clear
what the סתמא stama sounds like, don't even say the word כתובה.
Kesuvah. Okay, okay, where are we? Okay, ההוא גברא, hahu gavra, another
man, דקביל ארעא מחבריה. de'kabel ara me'chavrei. He... now we're finally finally
back to the משנה Mishnah: about stipulating that if I don't work
the land and I let it fallow, I have to pay you
for how much it would have produced. So there was a person
that accepted land from his friend as קבלנות, kablanus, sharecropping, and אמר,
amar, he said, אם o... If I let it lay fallow, יהבינא
לך אלפי זוזי, yahvina lach alfa zuzei, I'll give you a thousand
זוזי, zuzei, okay, much more than it ever your share ever would
have been had I actually worked the land. עובר תלתא, over tilsa,
and he worked two-thirds of it and he let one-third lay fallow.
אמרי נהרדעי, amri nehardai, so נהרדעי nehardai said, דינא הוא דיהיב ליה
תלת מאה ותלתין ותילתא ותילתא, dina hu deyav leh tlas me'a v-tlasin
v-tilsa v-tilsa,
that he should give him 333 and a third זוז zuz because
he let a third lay fallow, he has to give him a
third of what he said he would give him if he let
it lay fallow. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, אסמכתא היא
asmachta hi ואסמכתא לא קניא, va-asmachta lo kanya, no, this is just
a non-serious obligation, he's accepting on himself something excessive and he's not
really
seriously means to obligate himself and therefore it is not binding. So
the גמרא Gemara says, ולרבא מאי שנא מהא דתנן, u-l'Rava mai shna
me-ha detnan, so how's that different from our משנה: Mishna, אם אוביר
ולא אעביד אשלם במיטבא, im ovir v-lo avid ashalem b-meitava, if I
let it lay fallow and don't work it, I will pay you
with quality produce? התם לא קגזים, hatam lo ka gozim, הכא, hacha,
there he wasn't exaggerating. He says, I'll pay you what the field
normally would produce, so that's a straight התחייבות, hitchayivut, that's a straight
obligating yourself under certain conditions and it's a reasonable thing to have
to pay because it's what the owner was expecting, so there is
a serious assumption of obligation. הכא כיון דקאמר מילתא יתירה, hacha keivan
d-ka-amar milta yeseira, here because you're saying something excessive, a thousand dollars
and at most the owner would have gotten, I don't know, 200
had it been a good year, גוזמא בעלמא הוא דקגזים, guzma b-alma
hu d-ka gozim,
it's just an exaggeration. Now, okay, so he doesn't pay the 333
and a third, but he might still have to pay the normal
amount, especially, you know, if that was written in the שטר or
if we דרשינן לשון הדיוט darshinan lashon hedyot even if it's not
written in the שטר, fine, let him pay the normal amount of
what that field would have produced, but he does not have to
do anything about his agreement of a thousand, that clearly was not
serious. All right. ההוא גברא, ahu gavra, there was a man, three
lines before it gets wide, דקביל ארעא לשומשמי, dekabbel ara l-shumshmei,
he took land as קבלנות kablanus and the agreement was he was
going to plant sesame. Sesame is a bigger cash crop, you get
more per acre, but it damages the land more. זרע חיטי, zra
chiti, in the end he changed his mind and he planted wheat.
Interesting question if he did it unilaterally, are you allowed to change
the conditions? But anyway, that's what he did. עבדה חיטי כשומשמי avda
chiti k-shumshmei and it was a good year for wheat, and the
wheat he earned as much, you know, the market value was as
much as had he planted sesame. But, so actually the owner won
out because the owner now got the same amount of money he
would have gotten because he's getting his share in wheat and the
wheat is now selling as good as the sesame, but the land
wasn't depleted as much. סבר רב כהנא למימר מנכי ליה כחישא דארעא,
savar Rav Kahana l-meimar menakei lei k-chisha d-ara, the owner has to
deduct, you know, from his portion, the weakening of the land. If
it would have depleted the land and the land would have been
worth 100 dollars less, so the owner was assuming that 100 dollar
loss in his portion, so he has to now, you know, deduct
from his portion 100 dollars and give it back to the sharecropper
because he got the benefit without getting the loss that would have
been assumed. אמר ליה רב אשי לרב כהנא, amar leh Rav Ashi
l-Rav Kahana, so רב אשי Rav Ashi said to רב כהנא, Rav
Kahana, אמי אינשי כחישא דארעא ולא כחיש מרא, amei inshi k-chisha d-ara
v-lo k-chish marei, no, people say, better the land should be depleted
than that the owner should be depleted, meaning that the owner would
have preferred, you know,
it worked out well that the wheat did as well, but the
owner would have preferred to have assumed the risk of the depletion
of the land if he knew for the profit that he was
getting and he did not, there was never an understanding that he
would have been willing to accept less profit if you don't deplete
the land. He gave it to you to plant for sesame because
he wanted to ensure a certain amount of profit despite the loss
of land. He does not want to get less than that level,
so therefore even though the land did not deplete, you do not
have the right to deduct from that level.
ההוא גברא, ahu gavra, another case, person did קבלנות kablanus to do
sesame, זרע חיטי zra chiti and again he did a wheat, עבדה
חיטי טפי משומשמי avda chiti tfei min shumshmei and the wheat actually
produced more, was more profitable than the sesame. סבר רבינא למימר, savar
Ravina l-meimar, רבינא Ravina thought to say, יהיב ליה שבחא דביני ביני,
yahiv leh shivcha d-veini beini, okay, so if it had been sesame,
the owner would have only gotten, you know, the whole crop would
have been worth a thousand dollars, the owner would have gotten let's
say a quarter, 250. Now that it was wheat, it was worth
1200 dollars.
So that extra 200 dollars the owner didn't have a right to
expect it had the sharecropper done as stipulated, he only would have,
the owner would have, the whole total would have been worth a
thousand. This extra 200 is pure gravy because the sharecropper decided to
do wheat, let that all go to the sharecropper. אמר ליה רב
אחא מדפתי לרבינא, amar leh Rav Acha mi-Difti l-Ravina, so רב אחא
מדפתי Rav Acha mi-Difti said to רבינא, Ravina, אטו השבחא הוא אשבח
ארעא לא אשבחא, atu hashbacha hu ashbach ara lo ashbacha, he said,
it wasn't just the sharecropper's efforts that made the, you know, that
got that nice produce, the land. and also produced it and the
land was owned by the owner. So if the sharecropper decided to
change the parameters, at the end of the day, the owner's land
is still contributing it and the owner's still entitled to a portion
of the increase. Now this is all understanding that this is meaning
so the owner's always winning in all these transactions and what you
have to sort of ask yourself right is let's say the sharecropper
did the opposite. He said he was going to do sesame and
you assumed it was going to earn a thousand dollars and he
did wheat and it only earned eight hundred dollars.
Presumably based on the משנה, you don't know it's not laying fallow
but it is going different than the stipulation and there would be
a reasonable thing it would be reasonable to assume that the sharecropper
has to pay the owner the portion of the thousand dollar crop
not the eight hundred dollar crop because he didn't do according to
the stipulation. He didn't do sesame, instead he did wheat. So it's
not clear that that would be the case but it's not on
the other hand the גמרא isn't talking about when it produced less
and it seems like when it produced less that has because of
a choice not just it was a bad season but because of
a choice that went against the stipulation it seems like the owner
is protected. And here we're finding out that if it does more,
even though it was a choice that the sharecropper made, the owner
also reaps the benefit. So it's good to be an owner. Okay
now one more thing.
אמרי נהרדעי, Amrei Nehardaei, said Nehardaei, האי עיסקא, hai iska, this עיסקא,
iska, the עיסקא iska is a case of like a you know
it's like a silent partnership, it's a way in which we learned
this when we did איזהו נשך, Eizehu Neshekh, a type of a
way that you can have your money you know your money earn
money for you even without it being technically interest. So I go
ahead and I give you I I have money and I have
a thousand widgets and I give you a thousand widgets. You don't
have any money and you're going to take them to this faraway
town and sell them. And here they go for a dollar a
piece and where you'll be able to sell them you'll be able
to sell them for a dollar and a quarter. And what I
say to you is the following as I say you keep half
the profits and I get half the profits. Okay fine. If that's
all we did then in exchange for your labor you'll get to
keep half the profits and I'll get to keep half of it.
But we don't do that. What we say is you
half of this is a loan to you. I'm loaning you five
hundred widgets and five hundred are mine and you are just a
שומר shomer on them. And because of that when you are then
selling them and you're selling all of them together you're also selling
your widgets and my widgets together. So that number one makes you
work harder because you're actually selling your produce. Number two it also
means that if something happens and there's a loss and you know
and let's say I don't know bandits come or whatever it is
fire breaks out that therefore you have to suffer half the loss
because for half was a loan. I don't care if money I
lent you goes up in flames you still have to pay me
back. The part that was mine that was I suffered that loss
okay so if it all went up in flames the half that
was mine I suffered the loss the half that was yours you
suffered the loss and you're going to have to reimburse me. So
by making it a half a loan and a half פקדון pikadon
then what that does is a because half is yours you're going
to work harder and b it means that you're going to assume
half of the liability if something bad happens. Okay but now the
only problem is so now I basically put out money half of
the stuff I'm protected against loss and I'm going to get profit
sort of a way for my money to make money and it's
not technically a and it's not ריבית ribbit but there is a
problem it is a little ריבית. ribbit. Because I lent you the
money I lent you those five hundred widgets. Okay fine I lent
it to you I'm not getting any ריבית ribbit on it but
if I'm not getting any ריבית ribbit on lending you five hundred
widgets then why are you selling my five hundred widgets for me?
You're just a nice guy? No you're selling my five hundred widgets
for me because I lent you five hundred widgets for you to
sell for yourself. So that's ריבית. ribbit. So that's what we learned
in איזהו נשך Eizehu Neshekh that I have to pay you a
fee in order for you to do that work so it's not
ריבית. ribbit. Okay so I give you these hundred widgets or these
hundred barrels of grain or whatever I'm giving you or a thousand
of them. Half is a loan half is a פקדון. pikadon. I
pay you some money and therefore the work you're doing is because
I'm paying you some money to do the work even if it's
pro forma and you get half the profits and I get half
the profits. That's what an עיסקא iska is. Okay now האי עיסקא
hai iska this business
עיסקא iska פלגא מלוה ופלגא פקדון palga milve u-palga pikadon it's half
loan and that's the part that you're going to be liable for
that's the part you're going to recognize your half profits and half
a פקדון pikadon that'll be my half profits and my half that
I'm liable for. עבדו רבנן מילתא דניחא ליה ללוה וניחא ליה למלוה.
Avdu rabanan milsa de-nicha lei le-loveh ve-nicha lei le-malveh. Okay so the
rabbis established this institution of עיסקא iska so that it's good for
the lender and it's good for the borrower. It's good for the
lender that I get some To sell my widgets and I just
sit at home and relax and watch TV and I get the
profit and half of my stuff is protected against loss because it’s
a loan, and it’s good for the borrower cause he has no
money. And now I’ve given him all of this investment and he’s
able to make a lot of money and he’ll get half the
profits.
Okay. So איבעי למשתי ביה שיכרא. ibaye lemishti beih shikra. Now. השתא.
hashta. Now. דניחא ליה ללווה וניחא ליה למלווה. denicha leh leloveh unicha
leh lemalveh. השתא דאמינא פלגא מלווה. hashta damina palga malveh. Now, now
since technically though, those 100 of those 500 widgets are a loan
to you, איבעי למשתי ביה שיכרא שפיר דמי. ibaye lemishti beih shikra
shapir dami. If you decide you’re not gonna sell the 500 widgets
that are a loan to you, or whatever, let’s say, you know,
you’re going to go ahead, let’s say it’s not 500 widgets,
let’s say it’s 10, let’s say I want you to sell 20
bags of wheat, and 10 are a loan and 10 and 10
are a פקדון. pikadon. And you decide that you’ll sell my 10
bags of wheat, made a profit, give me the profit, but the
other 10 bags of wheat that I said were a loan to
you, you’re not going to sell. You’re going to actually grind and
make flour and make bread and feed your family. Okay, cause you
got hungry kids that you need to feed. So that’s what you’re
going to do and eventually you’ll pay me back, eventually I hope.
Okay, but you’re not going to sell them as I had expected.
Since it’s a loan, you’ll do with it what you want. So
that’s what we, that’s what the first
claim נהרדעי Nahardei said.
But רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says no, להכי קרו ליה
עסקא, lehachi karu leh iska, that’s why it was called a business,
okay, that you should be עוסק osek in it, that you have
to, that you have to like work with it and try to
sell it. דאמר ליה כי יהיבנא לך למיעסק ביה, demar leh ki
yaivna lach lemiasak beih, I,
why did I give you these 10 bags of wheat? I lent
them to you but for what purpose? That you should do business
with them. ולא למשתי ביה שיכרא, vilo lemishti beih shikra, not to
drink beer from them, not to go out and use them for
your personal usage. Now, why should I care, really, if you’re going
to go ahead and you’re going to still sell my 10 bags
of wheat? Well, I should care for two reasons. If you’re not
selling your wheat, you’re not working as hard to get a good
price, number one, right? Cause you’re not directly benefiting the higher price
that you’re going to get for the wheat, cause you’re only selling
my wheat. And number two is I don’t know if I’m ever
going to see the money again. If you’re going to the town
and selling it and bringing me back the money and we’re splitting
the profit, I know I’m going to get the money back that
I, for the wheat that I lent you. But if you’re going
to just use it for your family and you’re poor and you
got kids, then how do I know you’re ever going to find
the money to pay me back? So רבא Rava says no, it’s
a loan, but it’s a little also like technically a loan, but
technically it’s not, and if it’s a loan, it’s a loan with
these conditions that you can only go ahead and use it for
what we agreed upon. Okay. So אמר רב אידי בר אבין, amar
Rav Idi bar Avin, one more case, ואם מת נעשה מטלטלין אצל
בניו. ve'im met na'aseh metaltelin etzel banav. Another application of treating it
like a loan. If the person I, I lent the 10 bags
of wheat to dies, then these are now 10 bags of wheat
that I lent somebody, he died. You remember I said earlier that
I can only collect from the heirs of the, of the dead,
of the debtor, I can only collect real estate that I have
a lien on. So I can’t go ahead and take those 10
bags back. That was a loan, that’s his, right? If I lent
you $10, I can’t go ahead and take the $10 back, right?
You know, and if the person I lent the $10 to died
and this $10 bill is lying around, it’s no longer my $10
bill, I have to go ahead, I only have rights of liens
on the real estate. So that’s what, that’s what here רב אידי
בר אבין Rav Idi bar Avin said. That if the guy died,
I don’t get the right to claim back those 10 bags of
flour or those 500 widgets. I only have a lien on the
real estate of the orphans. רבא אמר, Rava amar, and רבא Rava
said no, we have to be realistic, that’s not what the point
of the agreement was. להכי קרו ליה עסקא, lehachi karu leh iska,
this is why they called it business, or to be עוסק osek
in it, to deal with it, דאי מית לא יהא מטלטלין אצל
בניו, de'i mit lo yehei metaltelin etzel banav, because I wanted to
know that I’m giving it to you because, you know, I want
to make sure that I’m going to get it paid back. You’re
going to sell it and if you don’t sell it, it’s still
my property and I can get it back. I don’t want to
have to trust, you know, deal with the fact that like you’re,
you know, you’ll do something with it and then you won’t have
the money to pay or that you’ll die and then, you know,
and then I won’t be able to collect it from your kids.
I want it to be used and to be sold. רש"י explains
technically here, the normal reason a creditor can’t collect from the מטלטלין,
metaltelin, from the chattel of the orphans, is because he’s not normally
relying on the chattel to collect from you only rely on real
estate, you know real estate will always be there. But in this
case, the whole point was use it, sell it, bring me back
the money, and yes, I am relying on this, these objects either
being around or being sold at a profit. Okay, so we will
end with this here.